Finding Aid for the Michael Pugliese Collection of Scores, circa 1976-1997
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Michael Pugliese Collection of Scores, circa 1976-1997
Mus. Arc. 15.2
Pugliese, Michael
7 boxes (107 items)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Scores and parts for solo percussion and percussion with other instruments. Most of the items bear Pugliese's performance markings. Others bear inscriptions from the composers to Pugliese. The collection also includes works composed or arranged by Pugliese.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Collection given to the Music Library in 2003 by the estate of Michael Pugliese; delivered by Jan Williams.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Michael Gabriel Pugliese was born Sept. 26, 1956 in Buffalo, N.Y. He studied percussion with Jan Williams at the University at Buffalo, The State University of New York, completing his Bachelor of Fine Arts degree in 1979. He then continued his studies at the Manhattan School of Music, completing a Master of Music degree in 1981. Once in New York City, Michael quickly established himself as a percussionist specializing in avant-garde music. He co-directed a 12-hour marathon of music by John Cage at Cooper Union in New York in 1982. His association with the music of John Cage continued, leading to his first performances of Cage's Etudes Boreales, Ryoanji, Voiceless Essay, Five Stone Wind, Sculpture Musicales, and Four3. This association with Cage also lead to work with the Merce Cunningham Dance Company as performer and composer. Pugliese toured extensively with the dance company beginning in 1985. He composed Peace Talks (1989) and Mixed Signals (1991) for the company. Other percussion works composed by Michael Pugliese include his Jinxed, June 22, Not Jinxed, Not Waves, and Peaceful Pond at Dusk. He also composed popular songs under the name of Mike Gabriel.
Pugliese made his solo debut at Merkin Hall in New York City in 1989 (the performance is available on a Mode compact disc under the title Perkin' at Merkin'). He appeared as a percussionist with the New Music Consort, the Bowery Ensemble, and the Michael Gordon Philharmonic. He also performed at several new music festivals, including the North American New Music Festival (Buffalo, N.Y.), the American Festival in 1985 (London), New Music America (Houston 1986 and Miami 1988), and the Los Angeles Festival in 1987. He was the founding member of the experimental percussion trio, Talking Drums. Pugliese also performed in the pit orchestras for musicals, including Miss Saigon, Nunsense, Jesus Christ Superstar, and Les Miserables. Michael Pugliese died Nov. 3, 1997 in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The Michael Pugliese Score Collection consists of 107 scores and/or parts. Some items are also accompanied by additional copies or photocopies. The collection contains at least 22 works or arrangements by Pugliese, including compositions for percussion ensembles as well as popular songs written under his pen name, Michael Gabriel. The collection includes 22 compositions by John Cage. Two of these works, Etudes boreales and Three2, are dedicated to Pugliese. Among other significant works in the collection are five works by Morton Feldman, including a rare copy of the score to Samuel Beckett, words and music, written as incidental music for a radio play. Pugliese's career included performances in the pit orchestras for musicals. This is documented by inclusion of the marked percussion parts for Miss Saigon, Jesus Christ Superstar, and A Christmas Carol.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by composer name and then by title.
Container List
- Albright, William Take that Jobert, 1974 (Box 1, Item 1)
  For 4 drummers with 16 drums
  Marked for performance
- Berio, Luciano, 1925-2003 Circles Universal Edition, 1961 (Box 1, Item 2)
  For female voice, harp and 2 percussion players
  Photocopy; heavily marked for performance
- Boulez, Pierre, 1925- Improvisation sur Mallarme Universal Edition, 1958 (Box 1, Item 3)
  For soprano and 7 instruments
  Two photocopies of vibraphone part (ms.), marked
- Brown, Earle, 1926-2002 December 52 Associated Music, 1961 (Box 1, Item 4)
  For 1 or more instruments
  Photocopy, marked
- Cage, John 27’10.554” Henmar Press, 1960 (Box 1, Item 5)
  For solo percussionist
  Some markings p. 3-4
- Cage, John 4’33” Henmar Press, 1993 (Box 1, Item 6)
  For any instrument or combination of instruments
  No markings; 1 leaf with timings inserted
- Cage, John 49 waltzes for the five boroughs Undated (Box 1, Item 7)
  For performer(s) or listener(s) or record maker(s)
  one handwritten leaf of performers notes from “Dominic”, with three leaves containing addresses. One of these leaves marked with pitch choices.
- Cage, John Amores Henmar Press, 1960 (Box 1, Item 8)
  For piano and percussion
  3 copies, all marked for performance
- Cage, John But what about the noise of crumpling paper which he used to do in order to paint the series of "Papiers froisses" or tearing up paper to make "Papiers dechires?", Arp was stimulated by water (sea, lake, and flowing waters like rivers), forests Henmar Press, 1985 (Box 1, Item 9)
  For 3-10 instruments or materials
  Performance markings; 1 photocopy leaf inserted; 1 handwritten leaf " A layman’s guide, by John Cage" inserted.
- Cage, John c Composed improvisation Henmar Press, 1990 (Box 1, Item 10)
  For snare drum alone
  4 copies; No markings; 1 leaf with timings inserted
- Cage, John Cartridge music undated (Box 1, Item 11)
  For amplified sounds
  Two handwritten leaves with diagrams. For performance, Paris, 1988
- Cage, John Construction, no. 1 First construction (in metal) Henmar Press, 1962 (Box 1, Item 12)
  For percussion sextet
  Score and parts marked for performance; Inscription by Cage
- Cage, John Construction, no. 2 Second construction Henmar Press, 1978 (Box 1, Item 13)
  For percussion orchestra (4 players)
  Photocopied score has markings
- Cage, John Construction, no. 3 Third construction Henmar Press, 1960 (Box 1, Item 14)
  For 4 percussion players
  Photocopy, 4 intro pages separate; score glued into booklet of construction paper.
- Cage, John Double music: parts 1-2 by John Cage; parts 3-4 by Lou Harrison Henmar Press, 1961 (Box 1, Item 15)
  For percussion quartet
  Score and parts; marked for performance
- Cage, John Etudes boreales Henmar Press, 1981 (Box 1, Item 16)
  For a percussionist using a piano
  Dedicated to Pugliese; two copies; 2nd copy heavily marked and bears inscription from Cage; includes photocopy of heavily marked score
- Cage, John Europeras 1&2 Henmar Press, 1987 (Box 2, Item 17)
  Timpani part only; inscription by John Cage; no other markings
- Cage, John Five stone wind undated (Box 2, Item 18)
  Photocopies of score; performance instructions
- Cage, John A flower Henmar Press, 1960 (Box 2, Item 19)
  For voice and piano
  Performance markings
- Cage, John Forever and sunsmell Henmar Press, 1960 (Box 2, Item 20)
  For voice and percussion duo
- Cage, John Four6 Henmar Press, 1992 (Box 2, Item 21)
  For for any way of producing sounds
  Parts marked with number of part but no other markings; 1 leaf with timings inserted
- Cage, John Imaginary landscape no. 3 Henmar Press, 1961 (Box 2, Item 22)
  For six percussion players
  Few markings; Plus one photocopy, missing p. 7
- Cage, John Living room music Henmar Press, 1976 (Box 2, Item 23)
  For percussion and speech quartet
  2 photocopies; larger one marked for performance
- Cage, John Music for Henmar Press, 1984 (Box 2, Item 24)
  For parts for voice and instruments without score
  Percussion parts I, II, III, IV; Parts I, II and IV marked for performance
- Cage, John One4 Henmar Press, 1990 (Box 2, Item 25)
  For solo drummer
  2 copies; one leaf with time bracket indications.
- Cage, John Radio music Henmar Press, 1961 (Box 2, Item 26)
  Inscription by John Cage, May 1956 – part of all copies; has a few markings
- Cage, John Ryoanji Edition Peters, undated (Box 2, Item 27)
  For single instrument and percussion
  Indication of mallets on instruction page.
- Cage, John She is asleep Henmar Press, 1960 (Box 2, Item 28)
  For quartet, 12 tom-toms
  4 copies, marked for performance
- Cage, John Sixty two mesostics re Merce Cunningham Henmar Press, 1971 (Box 2, Item 29)
  For amplified voice
  Has some markings
- Cage, John Theatre piece, Part VII Henmar Press, 1977 (Box 2, Item 30)
  For 1-8 performers
  Includes handwritten performance instructions mounted on two pieces of cardboard
- Cage, John Three2 Henmar Press, 1991 (Box 2, Item 31)
  For three percussionists
  For Michael Pugliese; 2 copies; 1 copy marked, other has no markings; 1 leaf with timings inserted
- Cage, John The wonderful widow of eighteen springs Henmar Press, 1961 (Box 2, Item 32)
  Performance markings and text written out on one leaf.
- Cardew, Cornelius The great learning undated (Box 2, Item 33)
  For chorus with various accompaniments
  Marked
- Carter, Elliott, 1908- Eight pieces for timpani Associated Music, 1968 (Box 2, Item 34)
  Marked; with additional photocopied pages
- Colquhoun, Michael Das Guiro undated> (Box 2, Item 35)
  Includes letter from the composer, explanatory notes, prose score?
- Cowell, Henry, 1897-1965 Pulse Music for Percussion, Inc., 1971 (Box 3, Item 36)
  For percussion (6 players)
- Creston, Paul, 1906-1985 Concertino for marimba and orchestra G. Schirmer, 1962 (Box 3, Item 37)
  Marimba part marked for performance
- Davidovsky, Mario, 1934- Synchronisms no. 5 E.B. Marks, 1974 (Box 3, Item 38)
  For five percussion players and tape
  Photocopy of percussion II part; marked for performance
- Dlugoszewski, Lucia, 1931- Complex suchness concert 1986 (Box 3, Item 39)
  For timbre piano
  Photocopy (1 leaf) of prose performance instructions
- Feldman, Morton, 1926-1987 Crippled symmetry Universal Edition, 1983 (Box 3, Item 40)
  For flute/bass flute, piano/celesta, vibraphone/glockenspiel
  Photocopy of ms. score; marked for performance
- Feldman, Morton, 1926-1987 Instruments 1 Universal Edition, 1977 (Box 3, Item 41)
  For alto flute, oboe, trombone, celesta, and percussion
  Score marked for performance; includes ms. percussion part (6 leaves) also marked.
- Feldman, Morton, 1926-1987 King of Denmark Peters, 1965 (Box 3, Item 42)
  For percussion (1 player)
  Includes two photocopies; 1 marked for performance; 2nd copy of score cut and mounted on folder-stock; marked for performance
- Feldman, Morton, 1926-1987 Samuel Beckett, words and music Universal Edition, 1987 (Box 3, Item 43)
  For chamber orchestra
  incidental music for a radio play; photocopy of ms.; marked for performance
- Feldman, Morton, 1926-1987 Why patterns undated (Box 3, Item 44)
  For flute, piano, glockenspiel
  Photocopy of ms.; marked for performance; signed from Feldman to Pugliese; “This score belongs to Jan Williams”—p. 15
- Foss, Lukas, 1922- 2009 Curriculum vitae with time bomb undated (Box 3, Item 45)
  For percussion solo with taped or live accordion
  Photocopy of ms.; marked for performance
- Foss, Lukas, 1922-2009 Ni bruit ni vitesse Editions Salabert, 1972 (Box 3, Item 46)
  For for piano keys and piano strings
- Foss, Lukas, 1922-2009 Time cycle Carl Fischer, 1960 (Box 3, Item 47)
  For soprano, clarinet, cello, percussion, piano-celesta
  Score and parts; percussion part marked for performance
- Glass, Philip Modern love waltz undated (Box 3, Item 48)
  For piano?
  Photocopy of ms. vibraphone part
- Gordon, Michael, 1956- Strange quiet undated (Box 3, Item 49)
  For for clarinet, percussion, synthesizer, violin, viola, and electric guitar
  Ozalid copy; marked for performance
- Gordon, Michael, 1956- Thou shalt!/Thou shalt not! 1985 (Box 3, Item 50)
  For clarinet/amplified bass clarinet, electric organ, electric guitar, amplified percussion, amplified violin, and amplified viola
- Harrison, Lou, 1917-2003 Song of Queztecoatl Music for Percussion Inc., 1962 (Box 3, Item 51)
  For percussion ensemble (11 parts)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924- 1994 Machine music T. Presser, 1967 (Box 3, Item 52)
  For piano, percussion, two-channel tape recorder
  2 scores; marked for performance
- Ives, Charles, 1874-1954 Circus band; Housatonic at Stockbridge; He is there undated (Box 3, Item 53)
  Ink ms. percussion part
- Kernis, Aaron Jay Death fugue 1981 (Box 3, Item 54)
  For bass/baritone, percussion, double bass
  photocopy of ms.; “For Michael Pugliese”
- Kondo, Jo, 1947- Luster gave her the hat and he and Ben went on across the back yard 1975 (Box 3, Item 55)
  For three marimbas
  Photocopy of ms.; no markings
- Kondo, Jo, 1947- Standing Parts I, II, and III Zen-On Music, 1973 (Box 3, Item 56)
  For three instruments of different families
  Performance markings in Part III
- Kondo, Jo, 1947- Under the umbrella undated (Box 3, Item 57)
  For 5 percussionists
- Kurka, Robert, 1921-1957 Concerto for marimba and orchestra, op. 34 Weintraub Music, 1960 (Box 3, Item 58)
  Score and part; score containsmarkings
- Kyrkostas, Mark Beirut undated (Box 3, Item 59)
  For concerto for piano and orchestra
  Photocopy of ms. percussion part; marked for performance
- Kyrkostas, Mark Firelight undated (Box 3, Item 60)
  Photocopy of ms. bass part; marked for performance by percussionist
- Kyrkostas, Mark In oasis undated (Box 3, Item 61)
  Photocopy of ms. treble melody part; marked for performance by percussionist
- Kyrkostas, Mark Shifting sands undated (Box 3, Item 62)
- Lang, David (David A.) Anvil chorus Novello, 1991 (Box 4, Item 63)
  For solo percussion
  Inscription from composer to Pugliese
- LeBaron, Anne The Rite of the black sun undated (Box 4, Item 64)
  Photocopy of ms. score; heavily marked
- Lloyd Webber, Andrew, 1948- Jesus Christ Superstar undated (Box 4, Item 65)
  Photocopy of ms. percussion part; “arr. M. Pugliese”
- Lockwood, Larry Paul Duets (1974) Paul Price Publications, 1974 (Box 4, Item 66)
  For 2 percussionists
- Mancini, Henry Theme from Peter Gunn undated (Box 4, Item 67)
  Ink and pencil ms.; arr. by M. Pugliese
- Menken, Alan A Christmas carol 1994 (Box 4, Item 68)
- Miranda, Anthony Eleven solos for the drum set 1979 (Box 4, Item 69)
  Ozalid copy; Inscription from composer to Pugliese
- Newman, Chris, 1958- After the bath undated (Box 4, Item 70)
  For xylophone
- Nørgård, Per, 1932- I ching W. Hansen, 1987 (Box 4, Item 71)
  For percussion solo
- Nørgård, Per, 1932- Waves: for 4 congas, big tam-tam, tuned gongs, marimba, cymbal, tom- tom, 2 timpanis W. Hansen, 1972 (Box 4, Item 72)
- Poulenc, Francis, 1899-1963 Suite française undated (Box 4, Item 73)
  Ink ms. percussion art; Arr. by Nils Vigeland
- Pugliese, Michael The beat won’t stop undated (Box 5, Item 74)
  “Words and music by Mike Gabriel; words and music by Bongo”; Music, texts, and instrumental parts; Ms. and typescript
- Pugliese, Michael Boy girl undated (Box 5, Item 75)
  “Words and music by Mike Gabriel”; Chord changes and text, no melody line
- Pugliese, Michael Hand of fate undated (Box 5, Item 76)
- Pugliese, Michael Jinxed undated (Box 5, Item 77)
  Pencil ms.
- Pugliese, Michael June 22 1977 (Box 5, Item 78)
  For 5 percussionists, 2 speakers, magnetic tape
  Ink and pencil mss.; Score and parts, also includes reel-to-reel tape
- Pugliese, Michael Not jinxed 1991, rev. 1997 (Box 5, Item 79)
  Photocopy of ms.
- Pugliese, Michael Not waves Oct. 1978 (Box 5, Item 80)
  For 8 timpani (2 players), 2 mark trees, narrator, tape delay
  Pencil ms. and photocopy;Text by Tim Cooper
- Pugliese, Michael Peace talks 1989, 1992 (Box 5, Item 81)
  For 6 percussionists, sitar
- Pugliese, Michael Peaceful pond at dusk 1978 (Box 5, Item 82)
  For 2 percussionists, double bass
  Ink ms.
- Pugliese,Michael Songs. Selections 1992? (Box 5, Item 83)
  “Words and music by MikeGabriel”; Texts and chord changes, no melody lines Big world(1992); Cats and dogs (1992); Dangerous day (1992); Goodbye today; I see a world; I’m feelin’ alive; I’m feelin’ down (1992); It’s a heartache; The pain is alive; Saturday night (1992); Save yourself (1992); Trouble.
- Pugliese, Michael Unidentified work (All whisper?) 1977? (Box 5, Item 84)
  Ms. notebook, with parts
- Rzewski, Fredric Moutons d’Panurge undated (Box 5, Item 85)
  For any number of melody instruments
  Photocopy of ms. part; marked for performance
- Satoh, Somai, 1947- Heavenly spheres are illuminated by lights Japan Federation of Composers, 1979 (Box 5, Item 86)
  For female voice, percussion, piano
- Schmidt, 1934- Zangezi poems undated (Box 5, Item 87)
  Texts marked for percussion accompaniment
- Schonberg, Claude Michel Miss Saigon undated (Box 5, Item 88)
  Percussion part; photocopy of ms.; marked
- Shibata, Minao, 1916-1996 Imagery for marimba Ongaku no tomo, 1979 (Box 5, Item 89)
- Smit, Leo, 1921-1999 Academic graffiti C. Fischer, 1983 (Box 6, Item 90)
  For voice, clarinet, percussion, piano, violoncello
- Smit, Leo, 1921-1999 In woods C. Fischer, 1980 (Box 6, Item 91)
  For oboe, harp, percussion
- Smit, Leo, 1921- In woods undated (Box 6, Item 92)
- Speach, Bernadette, 1948- Moto 1982 (Box 6, Item 93)
  For trombone, percussion, piano
  Photocopy of ms.; “For Michael”; marked for performance
- Stockhausen, Karlheinz, 1928-2007 Kreuzspiel Universal Edition, 1960 (Box 6, Item 94)
  For oboe,bass clarinet, percussion, piano
  Has small number of markings
- Stravinsky, Igor, 1882-1971 L’histoire du soldat undated (Box 6, Item 95)
  For narrator, trombone, clarinet,bassoon, double bass, cornet, violin, percussion
  Percussion part; marked for performance
- Varèse, Edgard, 1883-1965 Ionisation Colfranc Music, 1967 (Box 6, Item 96)
  For percussion ensemble (13 players)
- Vigeland, Nils Eleven pages undated (Box 6, Item 97)
  For glockenspiel
- Vigeland, Nils Evening 1983 (Box 6, Item 98)
  For flute, piano, trombone, glockenspiel
- Vigeland, Nils Evening undated (Box 6, Item 99)
  For flute, trombone, percussion, piano
  Photocopy of ms., different opening than above; marked for performance
- Vigeland, Nils Journey undated (Box 6, Item 100)
  For 2 pianos, percussion (?)
  Photocopy of ms.; missing p. 17-18; marked for performance
- Vigeland, Nils A line and its shadow 1988 (Box 6, Item 101)
  For four marimbas
  3 photocopies of ms.; marked for performance; c. 3 missing p. 10
- Vigeland, Nils Progress 1983 (Box 6, Item 102)
  For solo percussion and tape
- Vigeland, Nils Transparent things undated (Box 6, Item 103)
  For alto flute, percussion, piano
  Photocopy of ms. mounted on cardboard sheets for performance; also heavily marked.
- Vigeland, Nils Unidentified work undated (Box 6, Item 104)
  For trombone, flute, piano, percussion
- Wolff, Christian, 1934- Merce 1993 (Box 7, Item 105)
  For percussion ensemble
  Photocopy of ms. and typescript; marked for performance
- Xenakis, Iannis, 1922-2001 Psappha Editions Salabert, 1976 (Box 7, Item 106)
  Marked and contains ms. inserts; additional photocopy, also marked
- Latin drum techniques and examples undated (Box 7, Item 107)
  compilation of photocopies of ms.
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Percussions music--Scores and parts; Pugliese, Michael--Archives
Genres
Scores
Associated Material
Separated Material
The following scores did not contain any markings by Michael Pugliese. The scores were removed to the general collection of the Music Library.
Cage, John 0’00” Henmar Press, 1962
Cage, John Ear for EAR Henmar Press, 1983
Cage, John Four4: percussion 1 part Henmar Press, 1991
Cage, John Imaginary landscape [no. 1] Henmar Press, 1960
Cage, John She is asleep: duet (voice and prepared piano) Henmar Press,, 1960
Cage, John Trio: for three percussion players Henmar Press, 1977
Camilleri, Charles 1 percussion: solos/duos/trios Peter McKee Music, 1977
Corner, Philip Gong Peters, 1977
Crumb, George Music for a summer evening (Makrokosmos III) Peters, 1974
D’Angelo, James Toccata for solo percussionist Music for Percussion Inc., 1967
Dahl, Ingolf Duettino concertante: flute and percussion Broude, 1968
Feldman, Morton Vertical thoughts I Peters, 1963
Gibson, David 182 Norwood Paul Price Publications, 1975
Harrison, Lou Canticle no. 1 Music for Percussion Inc., 1965
Harrison, Lou Canticle no. 3 Music for Percussion Inc., 1960
Harrison, Lou Fugue for percussion Music for Percussion Inc., 1962
Harrison, Lou Suite Music for Percussion Inc., 1969
Hiller, Lejaren Machine music T. Presser, 1967
Hovhaness, Alan Fantasy on Japanese woodprints
Kondo, Jo Luster gave her the hat and he and Ben went on across the back yard: for three marimbas 1975
Korf, Anthony Blue rhythm quintet Paul Price Publications, 1972
Marcus, Bunita Adam and Eve 1989 (rev.)
Newman, Chris Final X 1985
Ruders, Poul Cha cha cha W. Hansen, 1981
Stockhausen, Karlheinz Zyklus Nr. 9 Universal Edition, 1960
Varèse, Edgard Dance for Burgess, 1949
Wuorinen, Charles Janissary music Peters, 1967
Wuorinen, Charles Percussion duo Peters, 1979
Xenakis, Iannis Dmaathen: for oboe and percussion soloists Editions Salabert, 1976
Related Resources
Michael Pugliese Papers, 1978-1996
Mus. Arc. 15.1
The Michael Pugliese Papers consist of copies of his curriculum vitae, a small selection of programs of concerts in which he performed, reviews and clippings, and correspondence.